Kevin, I am going to seat you tonight for
Leanne.
I see Anne is here now, so that
gives us a full board for discussion purposes here.
But Kevin, you're seated for Leanne Hutchinson
this evening.
Okay.
And so I see
didn't see roll call on here, but I see Scott Persson,
myself, Susan England,
Kevin
Arneson,
and Anne Creme in
attendance.
The
next item on the agenda is public participation.
I do see that we've got
a couple of
members of the public here tonight.
Anybody
want to comment
at this point in time?
Nothing
from me. I'm just here because I'm nosy.
>> Okay. Very good. Well, you know, I was hoping you would have been at the last meeting where we discussed the late regs.
What's that?
I thought you're doing that tonight.
>> No, we we
we voted on him a month ago. And so one of the things that we'll do is
we'll find out when we get to
the zoning agent's report whether he's gotten any comments on it. But
we are past the
public comment period and those should take effect here
on the twenty fifth of this month. So further on this week.
So sorry to disappoint you, Diane.
That's
>> what I get for not being everywhere at all times. But if you stick with us, we've got some probably
humorous
discussions on signs coming out so.
I'm always looking for humor. Okay there you go very good.
Any other public participation
tonight?
Okay, very good. I'm gonna move on to addition or changes to the agenda.
>> I do have a request.
An application came in
Hendy Road application for special permit from William and Donna Phillips.
It's
building in the flood prone zone.
And I indicated that I would bring it to the attention of the
commission.
When
did it come in Jim? Today.
>> I spoke to
Melissa from one
of the applicants or daughter of the applicant late last week and
she followed up with a packet
today.
>> I
would prefer
to not add that to the agenda tonight.
Well, I guess
the way that probably works is
somebody would have to make a motion to put that on the agenda.
Then we would vote
on that.
>> Does
it have to be like twenty four hours before the meeting or something?
The application
>> I prefer to do is we have a motion to add it so that
the way these things go,
if we vote on it and don't allow it, it would be
affirmative
as opposed to if you vote not to put it on and then the motion doesn't pass, then you don't know where you are. The way to handle the situation is to
make a motion, then we'll discuss the motion,
and then we'll vote on the motion.
>> I'm not aware of a clear cut regulation.
But different commissions have different policies.
I got.
Okay, thanks a lot. Yeah.
I've heard that I mean, with wetlands, for instance,
required
to accept things up to the to the meeting date. I've heard twenty four hours. I've never actually seen it.
>> I have seen it. Again, we're getting into we're discussing something that's not on the agenda.
The first
order of business would be to
make a motion to put it on the agenda, and then we can have the discussion on it.
If
we don't get a motion to put it on the agenda, I guess then
that keeps it off as well.
But I do have some thoughts on
why
I would prefer to not discuss that tonight.
Okay, well, I haven't got a motion to put it on, so it won't go on the agenda. And it is,
from my perspective,
the reason I don't want to put it on the agenda tonight is it is a complicated enough issue
that
I want to be adequately prepared
and I literally found out
that there was interest in getting it added to the agenda less than fifteen minutes ago. And that does not give me a chance to do my
proper preparation so that I am able to
address the issue.
And what is this?
Say again?
What is it that we're not talking about?
Is that Leanne?
Yes.
>> I heard you weren't going to be here tonight, Leanne. Welcome.
What we are not going to be talking about is the property on 57 Hendy Road.
Okay.
Thanks. Yep.
>> Leanne, I did seat Kevin in your place
before
your arrival.
And
I'm counting the squares here to see
if we've got
an extra opening still. One, two, three,
four, five. Nope, so Leanne,
I'm going to leave Kevin seated tonight.
And
you're welcome to participate in any of the discussions.
I don't think we're going to vote on anything anyhow.
But since I already seated
Kevin, I'm going to leave him
in that position.
>> Okay.
I think that's in the bylaws. And I'm sorry I didn't try to sign in a little bit earlier. But just so you know, this has happened before where
it asks for a pass there's a pass code and then there's a meeting code and it asks you for one, but it's really asking for the other one. You have to go back in and upload the whole thing
and put it back in.
So next time I'll try to start before 07:00 or, you know, two minutes of appreciate it. Because it's annoying.
>> Yes,
I understand that.
Moving on to the old business,
I see where I probably confused
Diane. It does stop Excuse me. Yes,
>> go ahead. Oh, just one more thing. Did respond that I would be here.
Oh, okay.
>> I misread that. Not that I would not. Okay, that was one of those reading the reading the email quickly just before I signed on and and Jim.
No, just I misread it and misinformed you.
I apologize for the miscommunication Okay,
go ahead. Yep.
>> So the update was on the late regulation amendments.
And again,
we did go through those at the last meeting and voted to approve those.
So I was going to ask Jim if any comments had been received back
on the late regs.
>> I did have communication with Linda Derek.
She indicated that there were at least one individual
on
the
other board that she is not on the
>> Yep, she's on Elma. There's the other board is El
>> Paula, and they were
caught off guard that the regulation had passed.
They were they apparently hadn't tracked it.
And
I
expected there might be somebody on
the Zoom meeting today to address their
issues.
>> Yeah, I would have been surprised that there was an issue, but
I thought everybody
from Alcoa and Alma were
supportive of it. But if they,
and I do know that
Mike Burke,
is the
president of Alcoa
did put, I think it was on Facebook that
there was, we were having a meeting tonight if anybody wanted to comment on it to show up.
I
guess good job on us for getting it through quickly. It made it go real quick when there was nobody
here to talk about it, but we did have it
well advertised that last month was the month on that.
Next thing I was going to ask on the lake regs, Jim, was have you received any permits that were affected by it so we could
test out the effectiveness?
>> Have not.
I did hear of an inquiry. I didn't actually speak to the individual, but
the gentleman that's looking to build
on the lake lot that was approved through Wetlands Commission, the former
clock property.
Yep. I don't know the street number offhand, but
but that nothing
has come in as of yet. Okay.
>> And then
and so my last comment on the Lake Regs update was
that
I thought I did the other members of the commission a disservice
by,
you know, try as hard as I could. It was late breaking news where I got the input from
Thad King and
I probably I did not give the other commission members the opportunity to receive that input, think on that input,
and then before we acted on that input. And I probably pushed a little too fast to get those
approved. But
I did want to get them effective before
a bunch of applications start coming in and then we
didn't get a chance to apply that there. But
I know that whenever
I get myself into
wanting to make a decision or something, it's nice to think about it for a little bit. And I recognized after that meeting was done that
there's probably some things on the regulations that are not perfect.
We will continue
to look at those as permits come in and we apply it and learn
lessons what could have been done better and we'll have the opportunity to go out and change it if need be.
We should have
I just wish there would have been a little more time for me to think about it, share it with you guys, you to think about it, and
then we act on it there.
That's something I've been pushing when I've been over on the
Inland Wetlands Commission as well. I like to do my homework ahead of time. And I'd like to give you guys a chance to do your homework ahead of time there too. So feel free to keep me in line when I start pushing those things. But
I do want to
make sure that we do the very best job we can in putting out the best product in there.
So that was all I had on the lake regulation amendments.
The
status of the lot determination
of Wheeling Road property.
And
I see that I have a box here.
Well, do you want to lead off the discussion on that, Jim? I see we have Mike Sheehan with me
here tonight.
You said he might show up.
>> Yes,
certainly.
Yeah, this property,
it's been on the agenda. It's been discussed a number of times.
Just to wrap, to kind of
give a little background on it. Property was taken
by the state
for the realignment of Wheeling Road. This is sort of separate than the swath as I call it, but the Route 6 bypass.
It was a piece of property taken
by
the Department of Transportation,
Sheeran property, for
the realignment of Wheeling Road as part of the Route 6 project.
And as we all know, Route 6 never
move forward. Property was subsequently
gated over to the town.
So
right now,
she ends have a property
situated
along Wheeling Road
with this
piece of land owned by the town given by the state
between it and the road.
Basically, it needs somebody we would need to cross this property to get to the property.
And they're looking at basically
selling it out, selling it as a building block.
It's
a fair sized lot. Believe it's four acres or thereabouts.
I think the town only and he's
it's an acre and a half. I did provide a copy of
the quick claim D
as well as the plan, which I'm guessing you
probably can't read very well.
I do want to clear up something in
the minutes of the last meeting. It's apparently
in the case that I said that it was for open space. I'm not quite sure where I got that there. There is a notation about non access line on the plan, but it goes up to a point.
And there is
breaks at a point on the plan and
that
they do have the email from the state. Hopefully that went out. People got it indicating that their intent
in the quick claim it's for highway purposes.
Also sent out
an opinion from Mark Brantz
on that matter and he.
I'm sorry.
Go ahead Jim.
>> And Mark Brantz indicated that.
He
did not have an issue with with the use of that property.
So that's
kind of where I am with it. I brought it to the Commission because I just didn't feel comfortable, know just something out of the norm.
I don't really think of it as a zoning issue personally.
So hence I brought it here and and it's it's back before you again. Jim, is it possible you can share all those
the maps?
>> I
am home with my
my computer is not working.
I don't know if anybody else. So
>> yeah, here's here's what I'd like to do on that piece of property.
Jim, is that
I spent some time
on three different things.
And so I'm glad there's
one or two Sheehan people
online with us tonight because
I came to the conclusion was we needed somebody
to present the facts to the Commission because
I looked at the assessors maps for the town of Andover
and I looked at our plan of conservation and development
where it has a picture of state owned and town owned property.
And then I took a look at the maps
and
I found inconsistencies
amongst them.
And when we get to the presentation
that I put together
coming up soon on frontage requirements,
I've got
some pictures in there. I did not put specifically
the Sheehan
property
site plan on there.
But we can talk in generalities about the inconsistencies
that I found and what I was trying to
straighten out. I'm sure the Sheehan's can enlighten us and make that a lot easier. So I
would ask the Sheehan's to stick around until we do the frontage requirement thing,
which is the first order of new business.
With respect to the open space issue, Jim, I know you got that information,
at least from me.
And I found it and I probably couldn't put my finger on it right this minute. I think it was
the map that you had gotten
that shows the state turning over that property to the town that talked about it was turned over for open space. But that's
I know that I provided that information to you. Okay, thank you. And so
did
and I didn't have a chance to review
the information you sent back from the Department of Transportation
guy,
but from their perspective, it was okay to put a driveway through there?
>> Yes.
Okay. What what
the gentleman said,
Conradoy,
he said it
it. It's on the quick claim it says for highway purposes and he left it. He said, they leave it to the town to interpret that.
>> Okay. And
I'm
not prepared to call up the documents in the middle of this. One of the things that
I've got to get some help with is
when I
so here's for you, Jim. When you send out the agenda,
if you can have the link in it
to the meeting, that helps me because I use two different browsers.
And the one that I can access the town stuff on
is where I pull up the agenda
from our website so that I can log in. And once I'm logged in, I can't get back to the homepage to maneuver it around as a shared thing. And so I haven't learned that trick yet. I'm using my iPad. I'm having trouble with my WiFi and computer. So
somewhat limited.
>> Anyhow, that's why I'm not going go back and try and look that up. I'll let you know tomorrow
where I found that open space comment and we can resolve it one way or the other. Another you mentioned, recall you saying it and recall going back and seeing it. Okay.
Hi, Jed. Yep. Just a second. Is my Hold
hold on. So Scott, you got the floor.
>> When are
we all gonna be able to share the maps and documentation
for information
for us to look at?
>> When I understand,
so
when I understand a picture
and what I'm looking for is I want one drawing that shows me the Sheehan property that wants to be sold. Yeah. And it shows the state property on there and it shows the driveway going through. So I'm
figuring out
what is the footage
going through the state property, well the town property now
to get in there just because
if we set a precedent with them allowing it for one point, is it going to come
next request
we get is to cross a two acre rectangle lot to provide access to a property. And I want to make sure
that whatever we do doesn't
that we're all happy with when we take it, we get the next follow on request that asks a little bit more than what we would want to grant for this one. So
I can
tell you I'll have that drawing next time. I'll put that
together in a little packet. But I am not nimble enough to come to a meeting and
get all that stuff
on the fly. If we did it in paper copy
in that, could hold it up in front of the thing and maybe show you, but you wouldn't see the detail.
And we've got those. It's just the
picture that shows the Commission
what the issues are we're talking about. I wasn't able to put it together on one sheet of paper and that's what I wanted to show and talk through. So
did somebody else have a comment that I cut off when I heard a couple of people talking at once? Yeah, Mr. Larson, is Mike Sheehan. Can I address the committee?
Yes, go ahead. Okay.
>> When we began negotiations
with the state DOT
a few years ago to purchase back the land that was taken,
Christina Smith made it crystal clear
that
it would be unlawful to landlock us from the building lot. There was
she couldn't have made that any clearer. That was one of the first things she uttered
that it was imperative to get that frontage back
connecting to the building lot because, again, it would be unlawful to lock us out of that building lot.
I understand.
>> So I don't understand why this is an ongoing issue.
>> Because it appears to me anyhow that you are landlocked.
So the question comes up, how did we make that
when it appears to me that you're landlocked and I haven't been able to come through that issue yet?
>> So
what would be the next step in reviewing this?
>> Well,
since you're here, you can explain to us why you don't think you're landlocked.
>> Because
we were told in no uncertain terms by the state DOT
from the get go that it would be unlawful
to landlock us
from the building lot. It's as simple as that.
>> Okay.
And
I understand that thought.
So
the question that I'm struggling with is how can you not be landlocked
when
the town owns property
between your lot and the road?
>> Well,
assertion would be that we would be entitled to a right of way to put a driveway through to gain access to that property.
>> And
I am coming
to understand that conclusion
and I apologize
for
how long it takes me to get there. But when we get to the frontage discussion,
I think
that thought is
maturing in my head. I have to give the other commission members the opportunity to allow it to
mature in their head. And we should be pretty close there.
That's what we struggled with. And we didn't have anybody here to give us the answer.
Because when we looked at it, we said it's a landlocked piece of property. Illegal to
make that subdivision that you had done. And we have struggled for months to get answers to those questions.
>> One
of the reasons it's imperative for we would like to see an early decision, we have a contract on the building lot.
The closing was scheduled for last week. Obviously it couldn't take place because the potential buyer would like
assurances that it's
put a house up. We now have another closing date for March 12. What is the
likelihood that a decision can be made prior to March 12?
>> I don't know the answer to that yet because
I
am
if we could come to the conclusion
that the
issue does not even need to come to the planning and zoning Commission.
And that's one of the issues that I'm wrestling with. And you will be able to hear those discussions if we continue on tonight.
But that's what I'm trying to
wrestle with now is
if we were to assume
and
our lawyer has said we can,
that we could allow a right of way through the property to get to
your property there,
then
does it need to come to the Commission? And so I think I've just got to figure out
now that
it's starting to grow and I understand your time pressure,
after we have the discussion on that presentation, maybe we'll be able to give you a better answer of what it takes.
I need to get some input from Jim.
If we make a decision on it, then Jim does it, how long is all that going to take? And
we'll go there. I would think that if it didn't happen at our March meeting, it would happen at the April meeting at the latest, that we would be able to answer you.
>> I just don't understand, Mr. Larson, why it could take it possibly up until April.
>> This looks like a pretty straightforward matter to me.
Well,
if an it
application
that came to the Commission,
we would not be able to act on it at this meeting
because
we've got to have a
fifteen
day
period where the public's allowed to
weigh in on any application.
And so then it
would put it off to the next meeting. We could probably
draw that back a little bit and hold a special meeting.
But because of the way the holidays worked out, the next meeting is only three weeks away from this meeting as it is.
And so I could and I'd have to wait after
the motion was made or if the
application was presented to us, I'd have to wait fifteen days. If there is no application and we are just making a ruling, I don't know the answer as to whether or not I would need to wait fifteen days. And so
my
comment is that since
this is the first night that we've had anybody actually show up to
discuss with the Planning and Zoning Commission the piece of property, I think we're doing pretty good. I have busted my butt to try and get ready to have this discussion.
And I've been fighting a losing battle.
I'll see if I can do better going forward. But there's an awful lot of
things that
haven't been clear to me to get me to this point.
>> Okay.
That's the first time hearing of it. I thought I was
handling it in the proper manner. And
>> you very well could have.
But there's not
been an issue that's come before the Planning and Zoning Commission
at this point.
Now, I think Jim's trying to get some help to make sure he's doing it right. He hasn't
been
in that job.
Know, he and I both got about the same amount of time. He's got an awful lot more prior experience than I do. But
I am certainly
my background is not in planning and zoning. I'm just trying to make sure
I
meet the intent of all the requirements
when we put it in place. And again, I would ask
I will give you an opportunity to speak again after we get done with the next presentation.
But
we have been trying to
work our way through this issue and get an understanding of what our regulations require.
And that is not always,
unfortunately, a simple straightforward
task.
>> Jim Hallisey, I have a question for you. Yes. Is
the property of the Sheehan's
The property to the east of the state's property?
>> Scott, I have a slide
in there that comes from the assessor's map.
And that was one of the questions I want to get. You know, I put that map up last meeting and we couldn't tell where the Sheehan property was.
Okay, I'm sure the Sheehan's will let us know tonight where where it is on that.
>> Okay, if if I say something inaccurate, Mike, please
let me know. She has had two two separate parcels of land.
So we're along
the swath of property taken for the Route 6 bypass
those essentially between them. The parcel that we're talking here is yes to the east of the bypass of
the of the portion that was
slated for the bypass.
So it's closer to Route 6. It's, I mean, that highway had gone gone through,
it would be this portion.
It's closer to Route 6.
>> Okay.
That's you're just trying to locate it right? I guess you do. Well, I'm trying to make it relative to that email that I saw tonight.
Jim, I think you mean Wheeling Road.
>> No, I'm just saying it'd be okay.
I just meant it's closer to Roots. It's the Route 6 side. Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
>> 6 Side. Wheeling Road. Wheeling is the north side of that. So, that would be the that would be the east side. Yes.
So, so the parcel that
that John and Mike are talking about tonight is to the east of the state parcel.
Yes.
That's the abutting landowner to the east.
No.
Yes.
Okay.
>> Other comments on this?
And again, I hope to address it better
a few minutes
from now when we get into the next presentation where I've
included a few of those
drawings to
bring up where I was struggling to find the correct information.
Okay.
Hearing nothing there, I will move on to old business item
C, filling of commission vacancies.
Susan, did you by any chance
go to sign up to be on the ballot as an alternate by any chance? Yes, I did.
>> I met with Carol Lee, who told me that
the way the process would work because the ballots had already been there had been two caucuses, one for Republicans and one for Democrats,
and they had come up with a preliminary ballot
and so she then put me in touch
with the democratic town chairman
Mrs. Lewis and I spoke with her
indicated
my desire
to be an alternate on planning and zoning and stand for the vacant position that was open.
And at the meeting of the democrat
on
Friday evening,
I was endorsed
as the alternate candidate
for planning and zoning. Okay. Excellent.
>> Kevin, had you
given any thought to
applying for one of the
open
commission vacancy?
>> Yeah, I gave some thought to it. I haven't taken any actions to officially apply for it, But I would be interested in applying for it.
>> Okay.
And so if
you are, I would recommend that you call Carol Lee like Susan did and
she'll be able to
help point you in the right direction
with either the Republicans or the Democrats to get on the proper ballot and get all that taken care of.
Okay, I can do that. I appreciate you stepping up to do that. Thank you.
And that was all that I had for
filling of commission vacancies.
Anything else on that topic?
I'm going to Can move ask a question?
Say again.
>> This is Leanne. Can I ask a question? Yes, Leanne.
Kevin, what political party are you? Republican.
Okay, thanks.
>> Okay, I'm going to move on to new business, the frontage requirements.
Mindy, I need you to allow me to share.
>> All right, just made you a co host so you should be able to share. Okay.
>> And
I promised everybody I would dazzle you with my PowerPoint skills.
And so here we go. Last
meeting,
Scott
asked me to take a look at
the width in frontage requirements
from our regulations
so that we could have a discussion and make sure that
we were all
happy with what our regulations had.
And if not, maybe we could update them.
So I did.
So anyhow,
the
I did find a definition of frontage
in our
regulations.
I
think 5.5,
point seven, point six is on the rear lots of our zoning
regs.
And it means frontage on a public street that either exists currently or is proposed as part of a subdivision.
And so the thing that I wanted to point out here
is if this
represents the access
to a rear lot,
this is not necessarily
the width
correction, the frontage.
The frontage is measured along the road. So in this case, the frontage is a little bit longer
than the width of the access to the rear piece of the property.
So that
was one thing. And we had come through this talking
about the access to a property over on
Pine Ridge.
So they
were a little
short here, but
along the road gave them the right
amount. Oh, you found that in the zoning regulations?
>> I did. Yep.
I
was tweaking on this presentation at the last minute because in one of the slides I said the only place that frontage was required is here. And then
sure enough, I find it someplace else in there.
What was that? 5.576?
>> Yes.
And I think that's
under the rear lot
thing.
So there is a regulation then?
>> Well, there is
a regulation that talks about frontage.
On a public street. On a public street. In fact, there's two regulations that talk about it.
Isn't five five the open
space subdivision section?
>> That made a liar out of me. So
I looked at five point five point seven point six and that's minimum
lot frontage yard requirements for ARD development.
So I'm a little confused maybe on where
that thing actually came from. I have to go back and
spiff that up.
But I found it. It is either in the rear
lot or
the two places that talk frontage in our regulations are rear lots
and open space
subdivision.
I think it is Section 49.
Okay.
What
is 49, Kevin?
>> 49 is rear lots
four nine dot three
So a minimum frontage of 40 feet.
>> I do see your frontage
note there right where you said it was. 5.5.7.6.
>> Well,
I will have to go back.
I was using the online version
of the regs when I was preparing this and
it may be off a little bit from my hard copy one year.
>> Yeah. But five point five
point seven six
falls under 5.57,
which is open space
and development densities.
Okay.
So it's
>> Yep. You're right, Jim. So, yeah, you've refreshed my memory there. It was on the open space subdivision
where I got the definition for frontage. It was not the rear lot place.
>> But there is, I mean, then it does speak to,
I mean, both in 11 to under the dimensional table.
Yep. There's frontage in there,
I think that's only or maybe there isn't a Well,
>> we'll
proceed on. Now that you've got that one, let me talk about lot width.
And this is in the definition section,
24.3,
it talks about what lot width is.
And it says a line of measurement of width is perpendicular
to the mean direction of the side lots and touches but not in front of the building line.
So when I took that to mean, I put a little building here in a lot
and I drew a line.
It's not really perpendicular to the side
of the lot because the lot is not a rectangle.
But I think you get the point that this would be where you measure
width.
And you want to have width so that your neighbor's house isn't right on top of your house. You have adequate separation there and that sort of thing.
And so
when
you're doing
most lots are rectangular lots and you'd say, okay, width frontage makes no difference.
So
I was asking myself,
why
would our regulations
discuss width
in that frontage?
And the only
place that I could come up with where it would make a difference is on a cul de sac.
Because on a cul de sac you have a fairly narrow
piece of land up on the
pavement circle there.
And it might not meet that 200 foot frontage where
this would be a good definition of ensuring
a good side yard on each side of the houses and that. But I don't know.
But that's our
definition of lighting.
And so
here,
I
took a picture
of a cul de sac and
it shows that yeah, you could have
less than 200 foot of frontage there, but still a good lot
and maybe that's why WIP was there. Don't know.
But I started asking myself the question, okay, so what is a cul de sac?
And again, we've got a definition for that.
In a town approved road with only one outlet having the appropriate terminus for safe and convenient reversal
of traffic moving.
Okay? So that
comes into your
understanding of what a cul de sac is a little bit. We've got a regulation that says a cul de sac may not serve more than 14 building lots.
And so I go back to
the previous picture,
and I guess that means you count up all these things and it should be less than 14 because
that's
what's on there. But we've got cul de sacs,
Pine Ridge Road, for example,
that's got way more than 14 lots on that cul de sac.
And so
I'm not 100%
sure
of
what that rule is supposed to do, but that is
one of our zoning
actually, it's a subdivision regulation that talks about the 14 building blocks.
It talks about a cul de sac terminate in a turnaround, which has a minimum right of way radius of 60 feet, payment radius of 50 feet.
And a length of a cul de sac should be limited to 1,200 feet.
And I couldn't measure those roads
from the drawings I had to tell if they were in excess of 1,200 feet or not.
But again, that comes out to our subdivision
range here.
There's Pine Ridge.
You can see it got way more than 14 lots on it.
Don't know the length of the road. My suspicion is it's more than 1,200 feet.
That
was done before those regulations. And that was
>> my
thought was that was probably the case.
So anyhow,
that's
what the cul de sac is where the width was.
Here's where we have on
rear lots. And this talks about
the definition of a rear lot.
And
we do have frontage requirement.
40 feet for a conventional subdivision,
25 feet
for open space subdivision.
So that's one place that
does have
frontage requirements.
Here is under the open space development densities.
And again, it's got minimum lot area frontage
near requirements. So it's got frontage 50 feet
for an open space development.
And this is where I had to change it because I was going to say the only place that talked frontage was in the rear lot portion.
And nope, found it here.
So the only place that doesn't have a frontage requirement
is in the
Andover rural design,
standard
straight out
property development.
And we can ask, is that good, bad or indifferent here coming up?
This is the
chart that Jim was talking about
earlier on and it uses
lot width
for all of these things where sometimes it's
frontage and sometimes it's width.
It seems like we were using those terms interchangeably.
But they're not really
interchangeable.
Anyhow,
this is this gives us
the amount. This is where the 200 foot width comes from.
Could we make that 200 feet of frontage? Maybe there's pros and cons to that. We'll get to that in a minute.
So
>> how did we get on this topic? And it really wasn't the Sheehan property that
took us there.
It was probably
a year ago. So things
we've been working on this for a long time. Here's a piece of property on Hendy Road.
And we were working with the property owners
on this lot. They want to put a house in there.
And
we all said,
can't do it. You don't have the frontage
on Indy Road.
Because this is a little piece of town owned property here.
And the homeowner came back to us and said,
well,
I've got this house over here
and the driveway comes through that piece of property out on the Hendy Road.
And we all said, well,
I don't know how you got there. It's got no frontage on a road.
How can it even be a legal lot?
That
was our approach. There.
Then we start discussing the Sheehan property.
And Mark Branch comes back with his opinion that we could treat
the town property
like the town property of a right of way and extend it in there and do that. So it's possible
that this lot
with
the amount of width
but not the amount of frontage,
given Mark Branch's
opinion on right of way and driveways,
that would be okay.
It took me it's taken me a long time to come to that conclusion,
But I don't think it's in violation
of our zoning regulations.
And so
I said, if that's
okay, and maybe that was done legally,
How does that apply
to this piece of property and how does that apply
to the Sheehan property on Wheeling Road because we need to be consistent
and fair
in whatever interpretation
of the regulations are that we come up with.
And so here,
this is out of the plan of conservation and development.
In the light blue
pieces of property here are town owned properties.
The dark blue
are state owned properties.
And so I don't know exactly when
the state
turned the property over to the town of Andover
that abuts the Sheehan's.
But on this map,
you can see where
the Route 6 corridor I think was going to come down through here.
And
it shows that it's still state property. I don't know if that was a mistake when we put the last plan of conservation development out or not. And so I blow it up a little bit closer to
the Sheehan property here.
And
I'm thinking that the state owned property is this little triangle
right here.
And
I thought I had the assessor's map
on here.
And I don't. I apologize for that.
But when I went to the assessor's map, it shows that this little triangle
belongs to the town of Andover,
we
had gotten from the whole discussion on the Sheehan property.
And then it has some Sheehan property
over here, which I think probably
abuts
up to where the corridor was.
But then there's another little sliver of property between the state or the town owned property and the property and
it says that it's unknown who that belongs to.
And so that's why what would be really helpful to me and I think would be helpful to the commission
is if we had a piece of property that showed
here's the piece of state owned property.
Here's Wheeling Road, you could see go through it. Here's the Sheehan property.
We give Jim a to make sure that
that description
is not in conflict with our assessor's map that doesn't show that little sliver between the two as being either the town property
or the Sheehan property.
And that's where I got myself
all
befuddled trying to make sense out of this today.
But given those three pieces, Wheeling Road,
the Hendy Road,
and then the other lot that was previously on Hendy Road,
I came down
to some options,
trying to wrestle with
frontage
versus width.
And one option is we can keep the regulations the same and understand that the town property can be treated as an extension of the town's right of way to allow access.
That would
suit the Sheehan's desires. It support
the Phillips desire over on Indy Road.
And it would be consistent with what was on that previously
approved lot
on Endy Road
next to the property that Phillips are trying to develop.
We could keep the regulations the same and allow driveway access to the properties via 824 referral.
Same end state, just a little bit harder process.
We
would have to make our recommendation
to the Board of Selectmen. Board of Selectmen would act on it and go that way.
We could change the regulation to require frontage instead of width.
This could preclude some building
lots
unless town property were treated as a right of way, in which case it would make no difference.
And there's probably others out there. And so that's
where I was kind of trying to get some thought
on the commission.
As I wrestle with all three of these lots,
really am sympathetic to the Sheehan's on
the state came in, took some property away, said we were going make the road. They would have made the road. They would have got the frontage on the road and there wouldn't be an issue. They decided, the state decided not to change the road
and they didn't give the property back to the Sheehan's and so I embarrassed it, in fact, to their cause.
I went
back to
this map and I tried to ask myself, how many other places
is there going to be a situation like this with all this
state owned land down here in this court?
And the answer is there's not many.
Really is a lot of this
is land between two different property owners that is open space and does open space very well.
These couple of properties here have
frontage on these roads.
It's really a small number.
And so
Scott, that's what I was able to determine
on frontage versus width.
It wasn't what I thought.
We had all kind of used width and frontage
to be the same thing. Maybe they're not
certainly width does not require you to have frontage on a road, which if you had to have frontage, you would have.
Where do we go
from here?
And I guess
the last comment I'll make is I look through Colombia's zoning regulations,
Lebanon's
zoning regulations to see
how they did. And at least Columbia uses both width and frontage and
they've got requirements for both of them.
Can't remember
Lebanon I know has frontage. I can't remember if they had width with it or not. But
don't think if
we go with attorney branch's
conclusion
that we can treat
the town owned property as a right of way alongside the road to cut through a driveway,
that's certainly all very doable.
So
I'm just trying to get
any feedback from the other Commission members on what the thoughts are there. Should we be encouraging people to develop land
or should we be discouraging people from developing land?
And that's what it boiled down to in my mind in these cases.
>> Are you looking for our opinions? Yes.
Well, my opinion is we should encourage people to develop this land and we should allow them the right of way like you would at any other place like Attorney Brandt said. We
all have right of way across
town property to reach the street,
and in this case, it's just a bit wider.
But we should definitely encourage development so that we get more people in town, more tax money available to cover our costs for things, etc.
>> That's my opinion. Thank you, Anne. Any other
thoughts on
the matter?
>> I have a question going back to the Hendee spot.
You
were talking about that house that had no access
and my recall was that
there'd been information that Hendee Road was straightened out that at one point it had the access and then there was it was straightened and that's when the town got that property.
Am I
misremembering you were
>> exactly right there
And
so
let's see.
Trying to find the picture that showed the Hendy Lot good. Here it is. So
I
think at some point in time Hendy Road came up here,
curved ground came back down, went this way. We straightened the road out here and that gave this little triangle of land to the town.
It is now owned property.
>> At
that point we essentially made that piece of property
>> landlocked as well. Well, in this case, and Scott is probably the expert on that, I can't remember if that happened,
if
subdividing
this happened after the town
owned this property and we straightened it out. So it created
unless we apply Mark Branch's determination,
it would have created
our
entering assumption
was that it created a landlocked property,
which was
unlawfully.
>> You know that those every,
I'm gonna have a different interpretation of what's
going on here.
I think these two situations that Wheeling Road and this one are completely different.
The Sheehan's,
the land was taken from them, they had that property as frontage.
So, they initially
had it, they owned all that property and the state took the property away from them.
So,
in that case,
I would agree to
allow that. But in this case,
parcel,
that
Old Hendney Road used to go through and cut across
above where that house is now and it used to go it didn't go up the hill went around
and came and followed the side of the hill through there.
So,
that parcel
road that almost comes out
to
Hendy Road,
front should frontage should have come out on Hendy Road because that piece was the town's property.
At the very minimum it should have got an 824 referral
from
town.
>> Okay that
house there Scott, is that the old Parkington house? Yes, yeah. Right and so they in there Yeah, so it was subdivided
>> and
they had a ton of frontage on the on Hendy Road, it should have just
used the frontage on the Hendy Road, but instead they used it on the town's property
which isn't frontage on Hendy Road. Every other house has frontage on Hendy Road, why would this one not have the frontage on Hendy Road? Yeah so when was that subdivision, I mean this is different, but
>> when when so that subdivision
happened when? Do you know? Well,
>> Parkinson's was put in there in you know '19
in the 40s, think their house was in there. Right and did they subdivide, Parkinson's? I don't think anybody
cared that they
they that they went through
that little piece of town prop.
Town used to use that piece of property to dump the sand in there,
so they used to use it and their driveway just went through there. Maybe nobody even knew where the boundary lines were.
>> My
question,
Scott, and you may or may not know the answer, if the road wasn't straightened out like this but went up here more Right, it did. It went up through there. How did all of this
land get turned over to a property owner as opposed
>> why did the town end up with this little? Well, it could've it could've come back into there at some some point, Chad. I'm not sure where it went. I just know I can you can see where the road that where the road used to go right in there. And I'm not sure where it went after that.
But I know that it
went through that. I'm just giving you the history of why
the piece was cut off the way it was cut. And
>> I appreciate the history because again, I think all three of these lots have similarities and we need to make sure that we're fair and consistent
with
>> each of them. I'm saying that I'm right.
I just have a different opinion about
>> these things.
The lot upon which the
former parking can house is currently situated,
I think was created
in as a free cut. I'm just pointing that out.
Yeah, in the not so distant past.
>> Right, it just happened within the last couple of years. So it was after the road got straightened out? Way after. Oh yeah.
Just a couple of years ago, road was, know, it could have been in the 40s or 50s. Yep.
>> So again and we could only surmise and there's no advantage of us doing that. We could have just brought that lot line down here then we would have had 200 foot of frontage here easy. Exactly and then that would have been to everybody's liking. So, the only liking.
>> Yep. Would have fit very quiet requirement
for the frontage on the road.
But right now it has no frontage on the road. It has a frontage on a piece of property and I can understand how you guys can think that that's
you know frontage on the road because it's town property and you could look at it that way.
>> Well,
it would make me ask the question, okay, so
let's say you've got a landlocked piece of property and it's not town property, it's somebody else's property, like the other side
of
Pine Ridge where
we're accessing this
piece of property through an easement through a private property owner's property.
So you
get to there's all kinds of where this can go, and I want to make sure that we have the proper bounding on the understanding.
And if we made the requirement to have frontage,
it would get rid of all that inconsistency.
I cannot say that this lot was improperly made now with our requirements not having a frontage requirement.
I would have liked
it to come down there. I think that would have been a whole lot cleaner.
But
the more I studied it, the more I came to the conclusion of
it's acceptable,
not the way I would have done it.
But I can't find that it's in violation of any of our zoning regulations.
>> Well,
at the very least, should have gotten approval from the Board of Selectmen.
Because
it had to do with town property. Anything to do with, you know,
non property has to go through Board of Select.
>> That
will come up there
in a little bit because one of the things that I want to talk about with the Commission tonight is
so if we were to say that on the Sheehan property,
this town property
was treated like a right of way,
It's town property treated like a right of way. How it got there is a little bit different, maybe. I don't think there's all that much.
But
why would that have to go to the
Board of Selectmen if we're treating it like a right of way?
In Bart Ranch's terms, it's just like any other driveway crossing a right of way going on to a road.
And that's his opinion.
Okay, yeah.
And we pay good money for that opinion.
Right, yeah.
So
>> anyhow, that's And I understand your frustration,
Jed. I get it, you know.
>> But
I just want whatever we do on Wheeling Road to be consistently
able to apply coming back here
on this property because I'm not sure and didn't have a chance to
look at what
the Phelps
want to do here.
But
that's
why we don't have an application. So I think we can talk about it from a conceptual point of view
of
understanding
that
it's fair to them whatever we do on Wheeling Road and
all that kind of stuff. So that's
where I am here.
I've heard Ann make the recommendation that we think
we
should encourage people to develop property
here.
I haven't heard from we got sidetracked
on a couple other questions here about this one. I haven't heard the opinions of
any of the other members on how we might want to go forward. I have one more question. Yep.
>> And I guess this would be for Mr. Sheehan. He had mentioned something to the effect that the state had said that it was illegal
to consider that lot
landlocked.
Was And wondering,
did the state give him anything in writing or is that just a comment that was made
verbally?
>> That
was a comment when we started the negotiations.
Christina Smith was the individual we were dealing with.
That is one of the first things she uttered when we met with her at the DOT office in Newington
is that no matter how this is resolved, it will be unlawful
for us to be landlocked from the building lot.
Nothing in writing. I didn't think there was a need for it.
Okay.
I figured she knows the regulations better than I did if she's telling me it's unlawful I was taking her word at it.
And that's because
it was
the sheen's property prior.
Yep so I got it and I
>> think that's the overwhelming
factor here and Scott thank you very much for bringing that to everyone's attention. This land was basically stolen from us
and
that's why I
just don't see why this is becoming
the issue that it's becoming.
The state allowed us to purchase some land back giving us access to the upper 48
acres
And this I thought was a slam dunk.
I realize you're addressing it as best you can.
You became
educated
on this situation, I appreciate that.
But it just seems to me the right thing is to allow us access to the lock. It's as simple as that. The land was stolen from us.
And
>> I don't understand I've said enough. Okay. And I wanted to add just one more comment before
we figure out the way ahead. In
our subdivision regulations,
it talks about you might
have a cul de sac
and then
at some point in the future, you would extend the road
down to develop more properties.
And in our subdivision regulations,
it is clear
that this extra land here
that used to be part of the circle
but now is not
goes back to the property owners.
And you would have thought
I would have thought that on the Sheehan property,
if the state changed their mind and didn't build it, they would have given it back
to the Sheehan's.
It would have been nice if
why does the town want this little triangle here? It was given back to the property owners.
But it wasn't
but I am very sympathetic to these little
pieces of property, and I don't think there's that many of them that
prevent
the property owner from doing
what's right.
I don't disagree with anything that
either of the Sheehan's who were speaking
on behalf of the subject,
they've got to say about it. I was
so caught by surprise
that
on a landlocked piece of
property in our assumption that we had to have a frontage requirement
and what it did with this other one. And then in my mind, looking at the three together
for consistency,
I just want to make sure we're doing the right thing. And so I understand it's going a little bit slow. It's going even slower for the people up on Endy Road there.
And I'm not sure that these have to come to the commission. If we were to agree,
if we were to make a motion and agree with Attorney Branch,
it might be such a case that
our zoning agent handles
all the issues and we hear nothing
more on it.
I'm a new guy, very inexperienced,
and
you don't even know
where the chicken or the egg come first as far as giving the Board of Selectmen an opportunity
to weigh in on this.
Thinking is that need to come up with our proposal. We
brief the Board of Selectmen on what we have done.
And if they want to appeal it, they got fifteen days to come back and tell us go back and take another look.
You thought wrong.
>> I
would hate to see our new zoning agent
make
a determination
without
our
input,
especially since I see what happened
with the one
at the intersection of Fine Rigginenity.
>> So,
somebody that's got more experience than I do can
come out with
a way ahead on
let's take the Sheehan property because that's the first one and the most urgent and we can have a special meeting
if it makes a lot of difference to
try and help the Sheehan's out. But I'm struggling to
come up with a
if if we were to make a motion that we I'll make a motion tonight to
>> allow the
zoning agent to make a determination
on
the Sheehan property on Wheeling Road.
>> I don't want it. Well, I so.
So let's
let's have a
does somebody want a second that motion?
Dan already did. Okay.
>> So discussion
on that motion.
Any discussion on the motion?
>> Yes, this is Susan, I think that it's critical to say that this is a unique situation,
it is cause the state had taken the state itself created
the situation,
and that we're attempting to remedy
the errors
of the state.
What did I say? Oh, I wouldn't call it the errors, but the ways of the state or the decision of the state.
>> Right I agree that it seems unique. I would just hate to see pieces where there's designated pieces of town land and people start carving off for your portions of lots and cutting across
larger pieces of town land to make building lots. I don't know if you could do something if you want to put a regulation for it if you could do something that says
you're only allowed to cross over x number of feet
of town or state land.
A suggestion or a thought. So
>> I
like the comment there, Kevin. And does somebody here,
whether it's
Sheehan's or the zoning agent,
know how wide the town property is, where on the site plan we had put the driveway across there.
I
>> do.
Roughly
it's seventy seventy feet 75 feet.
Does that sound right Mike.
Yeah, it does, Jim. Okay, I mean, you know, in addition, in addition to what I've provided,
I do have a copy of the site plan. When I say that it's it's a site it's a site plan that was drawn up with the intent of developing that property was never
before the Commission.
It's not an approved site plan,
but it's, you know, certainly concept, you know, it's it it shows how you could build on that property.
That's that's where I'm going with. Measured it. Mean, it's roughly 7,075
feet.
I
chose not to share that that plan because it just seemed
for one thing you know it has
it wasn't approved and I just thought I would not
wasn't going to clear anything up for any money.
>> So
if
we approve this motion, Jim,
well, I think
before we approve a motion, we ought to specify
in the motion
the uniqueness
of the
motion in that
the the property was taken from the property owner to develop
a
road.
The decision was made to not develop the road
and
the
property
was given to the town
and
precluded
the property from having any frontage on the road.
And so
we need to have the uniqueness of the situation
in
the motion because
we are going to hear
similar motions in the future,
maybe a little more, maybe a little less.
I don't know how it'll come. I just know that this won't be the last that we hear
of this one.
So with that in mind, I'm
looking for a motion
to modify the motion to include
the uniqueness of this particular situation.
I I so
moved, Jed.
Okay.
I'll start And
>> And again, for Mindy's benefit,
the uniqueness
is
the property was taken
to modify a road.
The modification to the road was not made.
And because the modification was not made, it eliminated frontage on that property
on Wheeling Road.
>> Would you want to say that we're doing this to remedy the situation,
this unique situation?
>> We
could say that we're going to remedy this situation.
And
I think any case that we get,
know, and there may be differences of opinion on other ones. That's why we bring it to the Commission
>> and we make a vote. So Mindy, can you go over that motion, please?
>> Yes.
So
the
initial motion
is
moved
to.
Allow the zoning agent make a determination
of the Willing Road property.
And second in and then
it was modified
that the motion of the property
was taken
to modify a road. The modification was not made because of this and eliminated the frontage of this lot from Wheeling Road. Are
we will remedy this situation.
And
it's just a unique situation.
So It'll sound better once I submit it. You
>> understand it and
we can go over it at next meeting also.
Okay.
So did we have a second to that motion?
Yes, I'll second it.
And that was you, Susan?
Ann. That's Ann.
>> Ann. Okay, thank you, Ann.
Any other discussion before
we vote
on the amendment to the motion?
Hearing
no further discussion,
a call for a roll call vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
>> Kevin?
Aye.
Susan?
And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
So Jim,
do you understand the way ahead now that we've made this motion and we've
tossed the ball back to you?
Okay.
I can take care of it.
>> This is Mike Sheehan, just very quickly, thank you. Thank you very much to you and your committee members for
doing this, taking care of it. Very much appreciated.
>> So now I'm
looking for
any thoughts on is there any reason to take this motion
to brief the Board of Selectmen on at this point in time?
And I'm looking, you know, there's Scott
and Susan
have a wealth of experience
on this commission.
And
Kevin and I,
not so much. I guess Leanne,
you're allowed to weigh in on that. You've got a bunch of experience
on these kind of things as well.
>> I don't see
the
board of select me can't make that decision about
I mean,
can they, Jed? Is that what you want to do?
>> It is within the bounds of the Planning and Zoning Commission to do exactly what we just did.
The basis of that is the opinion by the attorney that the
town property can be treated
just like the right of way on the side of the road.
And so
we'll
have to wrestle with that on other places going forward. But if consider
the down property to be
right away on the side of the road, I think there's no reason to go to the Board of Selectmen at all on this Well,
>> whoever
the landowner is gets
frontage
from the town
for two homes
for free.
You can look at it that way, Judd too.
Didn't
didn't have to use any of their land. They kept frontage. They used the town's plan for the frontage.
>> Is that a good thing or a bad thing? I
>> don't know. It
wouldn't be good if it was your land.
>> Nope.
Okay.
So
I'm planning to go brief the Board of Selectmen on the conclusions we come up with on signs, maybe not immediately,
but I will brief him on this when brief him on signs.
And I think
we're doing
the right thing.
Yeah, I've studied this thing to death,
and
I
can't come away with any other
conclusion.
Again,
I think the state should have given she hates the property back.
That's just me thinking. It probably should have. And
there you go.
Okay, well anyhow.
>> Any of the other board members have a position on this
other situation?
I would really like to hear some other opinions
because I, you know, I have one opinion and and I'm open to I I'd like to hear other people's opinions.
Maybe I'm missing something here.
>> I mean, think the one we just talked about is really unique with taking property away from right owner that had originally but artificially
like you're basically inflating land value by allowing someone to claim frontage
across
land that's
not really theirs. Is that what you're saying?
Yep.
>> I mean, who knows? I
guess we still don't have a real
answer to why this triangle,
this small triangle is left.
>> But
came down at an angle like that Kevin, because that's how the road came down. It came down at maybe, 20 degrees off of where Henvey is right now. So you can see that the road came down,
you know, nearly parallel with the pending now but off,
you know, 20 degrees or so. Can see why it's wide right there.
And then they just moved when they put all these new houses in here in the mid fifties,
they just moved the road over there, straightened everything out,
and that little piece was left and it was left to the town.
>> This seems really strange to me that the town kept that piece of property. They obviously had to take property from somebody else to move the road
to get they kept that little piece.
The town was all those trucks.
>> The town always owned that piece of property, it was a road.
I'm confused
>> right now about what we're talking about. So we've left Wheeling Road and we're now We're on to Hendy Road here to talk about this triangle.
>> And we must have if the road used to go like this,
this was not town property that the road exists on now. So we got that from somebody.
>> Right. It's just was realigning it, you know, whoever
owned those piece of property at the time was
Hartley insurers owned it at one time. They put in all that they owned all that property and they put into subdivision and all the property on the roads along
Andy Road there, houses.
>> Okay,
well, so
how it got there
is really irrelevant.
Did get there with, in both cases, townhome property.
And Scott has
so I guess your question is, Scott,
is it
too good a deal to be given the property owners your credit for frontage across the down property there?
So
on this corridor,
if you had that open space in the back of your property,
wouldn't that be a good deal as well? Nobody could ever develop that.
In fact,
I know
there's guys
at this meeting tonight that would love to have some nice town owned open space
>> property behind their lot. Exactly. It would never be developed.
So would I. I'm jealous. Yep. I can agree.
>> Yep.
Don't even like to bring the subject up
because
it's such a beautiful view you have out of your backyard there, Kevin.
It is what it is.
>> But that's
a good deal for the people that are there. It didn't cost too many. They've got a little extra buffer between them and their neighbors.
But I think
allowing people to develop of these, to develop some more property,
I think, a good thing. We're
not worried about the urban sprawl that we might have been thirty years ago,
but coming to Andover.
But who knows, with the pandemic, that could all change. But I do think
that the action we took tonight
is the right action on this
circumstance.
And
we'll treat each one on its individual merit. And that's why we have the wisdom
of
five votes, not just one vote.
And that's where we're at on that.
>> I just hope to see that people
might have chosen lots like that bought up to state owned property
for a reason, because they felt that they were protected and if it got you know, taken away or reassigned,
then,
you
know, that's obviously discouraging to people. I understand that we want to develop,
increase,
you know, revenue for the town. Yep.
Oh, well, that's Just
a lot to think about. It is. And
>> I wasn't expecting that we would make a motion
and all that
tonight, but we did. And I
feel good that it's the right answer, it
helps the Sheehan's out too. We're in a bit of a time crunch there. I think that's
a win all the way around. I hope we have the same wisdom
the next time that it comes to us.
Jed? Yes.
>> Hi, this is Leanne. I just wanted to make a comment because Scott was looking for feedback.
I think I remembered making
asking a question and I just found the minutes from the December meeting
about
talking about the Wheeling Road property and now we've talked about Hendy Road quite a bit tonight too. And I had asked at the December meeting,
if the board was
starting a discussion about whether or not we should have a policy
or do it case by case and Jed's response was that right now it's case by case and it kind of sounds like
maybe that's the best way to go because these properties have some comparisons
between them but I think if this happens again
probably there are going to be differences in each set of applicant circumstances or you know each point of view of the commissioner or the town. So it sounds like it's a good idea to do what you just did.
You know, and vote and somebody used the word unique regarding the motion for the Wheeling Road property. So Right. Yeah. I think right now, it's just, you know, these are kind of a coincidence right now. And as you said, there's actually not nothing on front of us right now about the Hendi Road piece. But I think for the foreseeable
future,
taking it case by case looks like
a better thing to do. We can still keep in mind the things we discussed tonight
about, you know, what we apply so that we're not all over the place. But I think when there are unique characteristics sometimes it's better to do it like it was done tonight.
>> Thank you, Leigh Ann. It's not a one size fits all thing. It is not, definitely not. And
I hope there's not an awful lot of them that we have to go to.
There are no. No.
Did anybody have an opinion on should we modify our regulations to require frontage?
Absolutely
Jed.
Any other thoughts?
When
did the frontage
get dropped for the regulations?
We
don't know.
>> Because I thought we still had frontage when I was on the board before, so I don't know when they got changed. Well, if you would have asked,
>> I think any of us
a year ago,
do we have a requirement for frontage? The answer unanimously would have been yes.
>> So
going forward, maybe we should talk about that at this
tonight's meeting then Jed about frontage. If we should move forward with
and putting it into our regulation.
>> I,
yes, I will, will do that. I, you know, I plan to,
at some point we're going to have a
public hearing to discuss signs
and at that public hearing we will
do a frontage change. I think that's a very easy change to the zoning regs. Yeah. I got to I want to go through. And if there are any other
obvious
problems with the zoning regs that we could fix at the same time,
let me know so we can
make those changes and talk about it and move those forward with the public hearing we do for science.
>> You talking about physically
having frontage or the use of the word frontage versus the use of the term lot width?
>> We're we're I think we are talking about having physical frontage on a road for a piece of property.
The on on
a road on a town road.
Yep. On a town road only?
>> Well, state road too. Okay. Any state road, town road. Yeah.
Okay.
And I think
>> we all assumed that that was the regulation. Right, exactly. I wouldn't have said it wasn't in there. Yep.
>> I was surprised and I was surprised when I found these little spots that
had frontage,
which made me think we assumed there was frontage everywhere when we put those things in it because we wanted to be consistent and we just didn't know. So now we do. We'll change it. And I'm not going change it tonight.
>> By putting in the requirement for physical frontage, can still handle a case by case basis, right, for unique situations like this?
Yes.
>> Yeah, we will. We've got the opinion from our attorney. We can
consider that.
And we'll take a look at each of these things on an individual basis, as we've been discussing.
Yeah, I think that's fair.
>> Okay.
I do want to and so I am going to stop this discussion at this point because I do want to spend a few minutes on
signs because I need to get some feedback
on the way ahead that I go there, too. So
I'll stop sharing there.
Okay. Look. There you go. Didn't want you to see that picture yet. Okay. Good. Nobody saw that.
Sign
sign regulations.
We're moving on to the next new business thing here, I think.
What are we changing and why? Our current
guess
or the Sheehan still on the line?
Nope, they got tired and left. Okay, that's Okay. I just wanted to thank them for their patience. I'm still here, Mr. Larson. Okay.
We're
not going to discuss yours anymore. I think you got what you wanted.
>> And I appreciate your patience. And I thank you for your
due diligence.
Never thought we'd get this resolved this quickly, so thank you so much.
>> You're welcome. I just hope it doesn't come to act to bite me somehow.
It won't. Okay, thank you. Take care. Thank you.
So on the sign regulations, our current regulations list restrictions
for political signs.
And this has been deemed a violation of free speech. Signs can have restrictions, but not with respect to content.
And so
what do our current regs say?
And I'm going to go through those regs here.
I don't know and I'm unwilling to try split screening with you folks now. When I work on this, I put both
documents on my screen.
But if I were to try and do that, something bad would happen.
Anyhow,
we've got a section of our regulations
that say all signs or parts thereof shall be clear of all rights of way
and no closer than 15 feet to a lot line.
And my assumption is that there
must be no zoning regulation that we violate more than that one.
Because
>> every little temporary
sign that somebody puts up in their yard
gets
into town right away right up next to the road.
And so
the question that
most
concerns me as I try to revise these things
is,
is that what we want?
Or do we want to follow our regulations
and say no signs can be in the town right away?
And in fact,
if we could make
an easy to understand
regulation that says they can't be closer than 15 feet to the road
because even given a property owner the benefit of the doubt, he's got a lot line that's up there next to the road and it would have to be 15 feet back.
And so that is really
before we
finish tonight, I'm looking for feedback from other members on do we or do we not
want
signs on
the rights of way or on the town property? I know
down by town hall and
in the school property
in the
dump,
hundreds of signs on
election season. So
there would probably be an uproar if we started to we would be accused of changing the regs
and all we would be really doing is saying no, we're going to go and actually follow them.
But anyhow,
that's the first
thing there. And this is under the section in our regs that says
regulations for all areas.
Going down to 23.2.1.
Public interest signs shall be allowed throughout the town and do not require a permit.
They are subject to the following. And it goes through here. In political signs,
in brackets I think after this was
political signs,
current event signs,
a bunch of different. Tag sale signs, all that kind of stuff could be a public interest sign.
And
where we were criticized
prior last fall
was they're allowed thirty days prior to the event or activity
advertised,
she'll be removed within seven days after.
Planning and zoning may extend the total allowable time period by ninety days.
And so
that would have given us
the authority to allow signs up ninety days before an election if we wanted to do that. But again, our regs were
they have some restrictions specifically for political signs.
So signs should not be attacked to trees or telephone poles, no signs directed so as negatively impact. Sight lines, which I think
all these signs alongside the road can hinder your ability to see people walking and all that kind of stuff through distraction.
No signs will exceed 16 square feet. Political signs may be erected
in the town provided the particular candidate is running for office that is listed on the town's election ballot.
That's
where we specifically talk about the content of the sign and that's where I think we got ourselves into trouble
on the content.
Not sure,
but that was a specific
requirement. It was probably
unconstitutional.
Anybody can run for office. They don't have to be
a
Republican or a Democrat
and not on the ballot, they can be right in whenever they want.
And the ZEO is authorized to remove signs of violation of this section, as it currently says.
When it was pointed out to us that our
regulations
were viewed as unconstitutional,
rightly or wrongly, Eric and I got together with the
Republican chair, the Democrat chair, we came up with trying to give the most latitude that we could.
And we said that on private property,
no time limit on when signs can be erected.
15 feet from the edge of the pavement,
32 square feet max for any sign. That's a four by eight sheet of plywood.
If there's multiple signs no more than 50 square feet, max height 10 feet from the ground.
If we're talking temporary signs
and you get back to the little vision of those
things we most commonly see,
we may want to put some more restrictions on these. And whatever restrictions we do for all temporary signs, that's fine. That would be okay. We just couldn't say a political sign could be this size, but a tag sale sign could be this size.
We also provided the information that signs on town property and rights of way
no larger than four square feet.
No set time up
or taken down and per usual no signage at the Veterans Monument, which shouldn't need to be anything different because that's down property.
Our zoning regs say you don't put any signs up there anyhow.
So that's what we agreed to.
If we were to look at a temporary sign, which I think political signs are all temporary signs, although you're right around and you may come to the conclusion some of them are trying to get to be permanent,
A public interest sign,
this is the words that we had, signs of temporary nature, sociopolitical,
education, civic, religious, similar activity or event, that's what we see now.
And we've got these novelty signs, a sign, banner, pendant,
valence, or advertising display constructed of cloth, fabric, cardboard,
or other light material intended to be displayed for a short period of time.
Those were the two things that I think we could put as
explanations on temporary signs and put temporary signs into our regs.
So I guess I go back to
I was out walking this morning
and I saw a temporary sign.
And
I'm
sure the person who posted this sign was well intentioned.
They felt sorry for a little gray cat that they saw wandering outside on a cold morning.
And so they posted a couple of signs on trees
contrary to our regulations.
Keep gray cat inside. It's cold this winter. And I just thought that was kind of cute. Was that on town property?
Most likely is. Probably in the right of way. Yeah. It's right out there alongside the road. So there you go.
So the question, do we want to allow temporary signs on town property, including right of ways?
I'm open for feedback.
Let me just share.
I don't know that in
Saturdays
maybe
it's not Saturday's, recent
Hartford Courant.
If anybody saw the article about anti Biden obscenities,
spark complaints.
And so when
we were
one side of me says,
I'm not sure if we're saying that freedom
of speech allows anybody to put any content on a sign they want,
I think it is maybe we don't want that on town property. Maybe we don't want that endorsement of this. And so the newspaper article
came about just at the right time for this discussion. And it was
profane
flags directed at president voters hang in Plymouth.
And there was so
the sign was
blank Biden
and all you who voted for
And so people were complaining about this flag flying on this piece of property.
And the conclusion was
free speech. The guy can put fly whatever flag he wants.
And I said, okay, well, there's been some sign everybody's
got their opinion on good signs and bad signs, but
I don't want that sign
representing
our town.
And so
with that,
my thinking was, as unfortunate
as it would be to
say,
yeah, we're just going to follow our current regulations, and you don't put it on the right away.
Can see the benefit to that. But that's just to share my thought with
all of you folks and get some of your opinion
before I
push on with modification.
Any thoughts?
>> Okay, thank you. Sorry.
I won't make it too long.
Okay, thanks. Bye.
Anybody want to tackle that hot potato?
>> I have a question that just from where slide there as if we allow temporary signs on town property should the restrictions be different from what we allow on public property.
What is the difference between town property and public property? I don't know.
>> I don't know either. In our regulations right now talk about they
don't make that well, they do make that distinction. We
say what signs are allowed in the Lake District and Andover Rural District.
And we've got some rules for them. And we'll take a look at those in a minute.
But that's all public property.
The question is, do we want to allow those same rules to apply to town property on the right of way or maybe put some different ones like we did? But right now, it just says
on property in the residential district. It does not make a distinction,
further distinction between town property and
the personal property.
Again, I wrestle with all kinds of things. Is a flag a sign? I don't know.
But certainly where you hang it,
got little flags out alongside the road to say
Merry Christmas, Happy Valentine's Day, Welcome Spring, all those kind of things.
I didn't consider that to be a sign necessarily.
But I do know that if we can put up feather signs at the gas station, those are signs.
We're very specific on what a business can put up and it doesn't have that.
Anyhow, I
think that was Anne asking the question.
And
>> I don't know that I answered it very well, but it's not crystal clear.
We can do whatever we want. We could make it specifically different.
>> A comment about
flags.
When
we had a business in West Hartford years back,
we wanted to put out an open sign, a flag that said open.
And the town said, no, we could not put out
that kind of a sign. They allowed it like within thirty days of a grand opening of a store.
But
they could not prohibit us from flying the American flag.
So that's what we would put out every day to show that we were open. We put out the American flag. Yep and so
>> as I read through,
you one, I was surprised that we had zoning regulations that covered signs. I didn't know that that was our can of worms to enforce.
There are probably,
I can think
of very
few occasions
I can only think of one occasion
where any discussion has come up in a planning and zoning meeting on
signs. It was when
the gas station down at the end of Lake Road went a little crazy putting up those feather signs out there. They must have had 10 of them alongside the road. And
we took issue with that.
But I think that
it's
not very often that somebody comes up with a sign,
with the exception of these little temporary signs that everybody routinely
puts out in front of their house. When I was talking to Eric about this last fall when we were wrestling with this,
know,
how long a temporary sign should be up,
he made the comment that he thinks the last of the
signs in opposition to the gas
transfer station down at the Christmas tree farm
may not be down yet. That's probably an issue that's two years old.
And so some of those temporary signs have been up for a long time.
And I think that
if we want to have temporary signs and we limit the length,
that's all good and well.
But again, looking for some
feedback.
We allow
it? The
first and biggest issue is do we want those temporary signs on town property or do we want the people to put them 15 feet back from the road on their own property? Property.
No and yes.
Okay.
And I think that was Leanne?
Yes.
Okay.
Got it.
Any other thoughts?
>> No, I agree with Leanne, but then what happens when you have something
like the library that wants to put a sign out that they're having a book sale or
some sort of event happening there?
Think the library Does that
fit into do we allow temporary signs on town property?
Well doesn't the library have a permanent sign?
They have a permanent sign that says library. Okay.
>> I would think they would dangle it from
that maybe. I don't know.
They did have like a whiteboard
Yeah. At one
>> They are in the business district, which is a little different.
Okay. But we're talking really, I'm
looking for
it's a
good question. We need to make sure we cover the bases.
>> And school does the same thing. School sometimes And puts
so you have to be careful if you're saying we don't allow temporary signs on town property. They can say, well, the school just put something up for soccer registration.
>> Yep.
They've got the
permanent sign where they change the letters and make it reflect whatever they want to say, too.
I'm really talking about these little two foot by two foot
square things that people
poke in the ground. No, I understand.
>> Unless you're saying no, we're not allowing these temporary things on town property, then
someone could bring up, well, you're
>> not being fair to us. That is the other side of the double edged sword. And
we wouldn't even be talking about this if it hadn't been somebody fussed for the fact that we restricting
their free speech on political science.
>> Well, this is Leanne again. This
is a two part comment.
I see what Susan means. I was thinking in terms when I said no on town property of things like
political science, although, like you said, the the having him outside the dump is kind of a time town
time honored thing to do. Yep. But, I mean, that's a it gets back to the question of who appears on our ballot.
And then,
you know, somebody could put up
probably,
I don't know, I'm just thinking out loud now,
about
supposedly,
I guess, any political candidate could be controversial,
not just the last presidential election that we had where if somebody was put up a sign for one major candidate or the other and then other people took offense because they had no intention of voting for the person.
But as somebody said, you know, we do I think it was you, Jed. We have many, many signs outside the dump during our local election
season.
So I think one question brings up another one like, you know, we probably don't wanna restrict
signs at the school and the library advertising
their auction.
And the other thing that brings up is when we started talking,
I think your first slide
and this might be jumping around a bit, but I think your first slide about this was about the political signs
and somebody challenging somebody in town last fall
about the signs went up very early last fall. And I thought Scott said something about something that coming down from the state
because of the pandemic and the early voting and,
you know, the circumstances were different last year.
So I don't know where that came from. Was that one discussion? Because we started talking about political signs about
how early the science themselves could go up
and then about free speech about that was another topic at the beginning of this discussion about what you can have on the science so we're kind of talking about two or three different things Leanne, do you remember the whole reason we had the comment
>> about
being on the Andover ballot or whatever was because about fifteen or twenty years ago people from Willamantic and other towns
posting all their signs to Andover because people drove through Route 6
and they wanted to get the coverage. You'd be driving down Route 6 and you'd be seeing all these election signs for people running in Willamantic or Colchester.
And that was part of that was the reason that language was put in there was not against
specific political candidates that we all voted for that were on our ballot. It was for people that we would never even be able to vote for. They just were putting the signs there.
>> Yeah,
so one question kind of brings up another question. Is there something Scott,
I think you
brought this up when I because I questioned the signs last fall. I didn't know why they were going up so early and I thought people were doing it wrong because with this commission enforces it.
Then I Scott, I thought you said something came down from the governor's office about, again, with the early voting and the just the whole complexion of the election season being different last year that the town was specifically told that they can go up that much earlier?
>> Mean, is that correct? It could have been at
that time, yeah.
I can't remember exact stuff,
>> but I I think you might be right, Leanne. I think the discussion was that there was a case
someplace else in the state, and I don't know where
it went to court and
the restrictions on a political sign being different than other content sign
made the regulations unconstitutional.
So the advice we got from our attorney
was that,
yes, our regulations are currently unconstitutional
because they put different requirements
on political signs than other signs and a sign is a sign.
I do. I mean, I think. Yeah. And when
>> hate to
do away with putting up the little league signs and the big sale signs and
there's a lot of good signs out there. And
I can
be happy with if we were to put and is it within our right
on thirty days, sixty days, whatever we want before the event, take it down seven days after,
that is all fine and dandy. But that means that that
that goes for all those little signs,
not
just some signs. When somebody puts up a sign we don't like,
it is up there for whatever
we say. And that is the price we pay
to continue to allow the signs to go up that
we do want to have up there.
Because we can't regulate the content.
>> Well, I think as long as we can enforce that and nobody says it violates their free speech, that seemed to be one of the questions we started out with. You know? Because otherwise, you're gonna get a lot of visual clutter. Like you said, there's gonna be theoretically, there could be signs everywhere, but
I don't know. It it's I like the idea as long as it's enforceable of kind of do what we've been doing with this thirty days for the temporary signs like tag sales and
library auctions and steak dinners and free puppies and things like that. Okay.
Good. And
what's everybody else think?
>> I have a thought of
when we're saying things like allowing the library to put up a sign or the school looking at the sign,
that is on even though it's town property it's like the school's putting it on their own piece of property there and the library's putting it on their own.
I don't know if that's
not being fair to other people because
you know they're limiting who can put a sign on that property.
The other thought would be could you
require people that want to put signs up like that like the library or the school or soccer
teams and they ask them to get a permit
to get that sign to put that up. I know it would be a bit more
work probably to allow them then.
You
limit the signs by asking them to get a permit every time they want to put one up?
>> Certainly, if it's going to be a permanent sign, it takes a permit.
And
I am not aware of any
permit applications
for signs that have come in a
long, long time.
>> I mean, just to put up a sign saying we're going to have a
potluck dinner,
you know stay at the church
would they then get a permit to put the sign up on their corner there.
Yep. But that would prohibit other people from putting up little political signs because they would not be given a permit.
Or can't we limit them? Who can we get permits I don't think for these little temporary signs
>> that people put up, we want to get into the permit business. We can't get Jim bogged down
with that. He's going to have his hands full just in force and taken down sides as he goes throughout Dallas after they've been up for a while.
Okay. Sorry about that. So
>> there are signs that we like.
It
do we think it's reasonable to require them to be 15 feet back from the edge of the road?
You know, that would accommodate
the library, the school, the dump.
People can put the signs in their front yards. I know there's a couple of yards where
you don't have a good place close to the road because it's very steep embankment or something.
But
that's too bad. We
can just say that. I guess and I was surprised as I walked around, I saw signs
right up next to the other property over here, right up to the boundary line. And I like 15 feet away so we can make sure we know who's expressing the opinion
there.
And keep it 15 feet from all your
property lines.
>> Any thought on that being good or bad? That sounds like a good I like the 15 foot. You're
>> never going to I shouldn't say never, but you're rarely gonna obstruct line of sight from a road. Yeah.
You don't you don't don't get as much conflict. It's just the
the private, you know, the side, the other signs
on public property is
I have no idea how you address that without
>> singling out. And I don't know whose property it was, but as you turn on to School Road off of Lake Road around election season,
man, there are so many signs out there. It's crazy. I don't know if that's town right away property, town property or private property. But
certainly, I
think if we kept 15 feet back from the road, that sounds
reasonable.
feet from a property line also.
>> Yeah, I kind of like that. If
you want to sign, put it right there in front of your house.
Be proud of that baby.
Exactly.
>> I still think 15 feet is quite far back if you're going from the pavement.
I would think 10 feet would be far enough to
keep it away from the street, yet people would still be able to see the sign.
>> I don't think people are going to go by 15 feet because you can't see the signs many times. I picked 15 feet, one, because that's what our regulation currently says. And two, it's consistent with the side yard. We could change it to 10 feet from any lot line
and that's fine as well. I also know that
if you're 15 feet back from the road,
there's a very good chance that you're not in the town's right of way.
And
so if
we put a sign don't put it in the town's right of way, somebody will say well how big is the right of way? And that's
a question that I don't always have the answer to.
>> Right. Probably different in
every road and every section of road. Yep. And so
>> whatever distance
we pick, we ought to just apply it consistently
and go from there.
>> I mean, everyone should be able to meet the 15 feet because nobody can build anything closer than 15 feet to the road anyways, right?
Right.
So Not
always, setbacks are all different.
>> I've got a stone wall in the middle of my right away, I'm sure.
And I don't know how big it is on Lake Road, but right
off the road, a stone wall has been there longer than the road has.
But there are signs
in the right of way.
Next month when we get together, I will have pictures of various
signs that
we can discuss.
For instance, the fire department sells
signs with your house number on it.
And I think most properties have that in the town right away out by the road because you want it very visible. So when the ambulance is trying to find you in the middle of the night, they see the property marker out there. I would think that would be one that we would specifically
want to allow. And we can't.
I
think we're
just trying to focus in on these little things that we pop up there. And I particularly did not want to discuss this issue until we got closer
to the end of the pandemic because I love all the little signs up there acknowledging the efforts of our frontline workers and the nurses and first responders
and all that. And I didn't want to do anything that would be detrimental to that cause.
But I think that by the time we get this done,
hopefully that will be history,
and
we'll be moving forward.
I think I got enough input from the group to allow me to go out and
tweak on our current regulations.
If there's any other issues on any other signs
that
well, I'll go through the rest of the questions here. I think we've covered them all. Do we want to put time limits on how long a temporary sign could be up?
And I think the answer is yes.
We can talk about thirty, sixty, ninety days,
but it's going be one size fits all, that'll be Okay.
What kind of sign restriction should there be on temporary signs?
Some of the political signs
are a little bigger.
Is that okay?
Again, I don't think if we allow a bigger sign there, that will necessarily impact the majority of the signs. We'll still be the little stick them in the ground
cardboard on two stakes and be there.
If we allow temporary signs on town property, should the restrictions be different than what we allow on public property? And I think
somebody was discussing that before. The other thing that came up, and I have a specific example,
what about a home based business?
And
as I walk around, there is a permanent sign out.
I'll measure how far it is from the road, but
it's about a home based business and
very nice sign.
But right this minute, we don't have any allowance for anything like that. How far off the road is it, Jed? Well, it's probably 10 to 15 feet.
I'll go measure for sure so I know. I would hate to have to have them move them. I guess we could grandfather it.
It's Sears landscaping
on
Lake Road.
Probably up on School Road coming down into Lakeside Drive.
But
very
nice sign. We just don't have any regulations that talk about
home based businesses.
And most of them you probably don't need to.
But as I think about sign regulations,
I think about all the signs I see as I walk around
and say,
how is this
affected by our Right, yeah.
>> So is that one
out of the right of way?
>> I think it is.
It's probably close. I don't know because I don't know how big the right of way is on that particular road up there.
It's between ten and fifteen feet back and it's a reasonable distance back from the road that
is good. I'll go measure it and find out what it is.
>> Great examples are that's a good thing to get examples and then
get you thinking about the different
signs that we could find.
>> Okay.
And again, this is not anything urgent. I just wanted to
get you thinking about it so that when
I come forward with
something
and again, just because I draft it up
doesn't mean it's right. It just means
an ability to foster a little discussion there.
But I'm going to focus on those little temporary signs because I don't think we've had any issues with the
bigger signs.
Okay, and
with it starting to
get a little late in the night, I'm going to close that
discussion.
>> This is Leanne. I'm not seated. Could I be excused?
You can be excused, yes.
>> Okay. I'm going to leave the meeting. Thank you. Unless
>> you want to stick around for the zoning agent's
report.
But that's up to you.
Well, is it let me see.
Is it next?
>> We're going to have a couple of minutes. Let me go into the zoning.
Within five minutes, we'll be there.
>> Okay. I just had a comment about one of the workshops. That was all.
>> Okay.
And I think Jim's going to talk about that, too. So why don't you save that for then, and we'll
be there.
Okay. I'll hang on. The
>> next item is approval of the minutes from our last meeting on January 25.
>> I move approval of the minutes
Thank you, Susan. January 26.
Looking
for a second?
I'll second it. Thank you, Scott.
>> Any comments on the minutes?
I just got a couple here, Mindy.
On the first page,
item two
on the second paragraph there,
the last sentence,
The tan orange color is Zone D.
It currently says it is in the Lake District but outside the watershed.
It should say it's outside the Lake District but within the watershed.
And then going down a couple more paragraphs down on that same
section.
Jim Hollisley suggested the adoptive date for the regulations be tonight.
And the adoptive date would be a month from now. The
second adoptive should be effective.
Thank you.
>> On
page three,
the top sentence there, the proposed amendment will provide the town an additional tool to preserve
and it's
I crossed it out there. I think it's an or which
should be removed. So it just says to preserve the water quality of Andover Lake.
And then on that same page under filing of vacancies,
the second sentence there,
Susan England will
not be
rerunning.
I thought we could just say running.
>> And also on that, should it be filling of vacancies?
Not filing of vacancies?
>> Yes. Oh, yep. Very
good. Thank
you.
And then on
the last page, page four of the second paragraph, Jim Hollisley stated that
him and the building official, I think better might be he and the building official.
But I'm not an English
major, so
I could be wrong but it just sounded better to me. And that was all the comments I had. Anybody else have anything on that?
In that case,
call for a vote
on approving those. Anne?
Aye. Scott?
Aye.
Kevin?
Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The minutes are approved, five-zero-zero.
Any correspondence,
Jim?
No correspondence.
Okay.
We're moving on to the zoning agent's report.
>> Okay. I have
I sent out
an email, it was actually from Megan initially on three workshops held by CLEAR out of Yukon.
Zoning Atlas went on Long Island Sound and
went on JS coordination.
And once again, if any
members are interested in attending,
if there are fees associated with these workshops, we can generally cover them. I'm not sure if the CLEAR ones,
the CLEAR workshops,
if there's any costs associated with them.
There was another one that I sent out
on the use of
an app on your phone. I don't
have the information on that. I apologize, but that should have gone out today.
Moving on to enforcement
action.
Whales Road
was somebody using a
RV for temporary. I had sent out
cease and desist a while back that
date came and went,
referred matter to the town attorney who sent out
a follow-up cease and desist. I got a call today from
the owner of the property, Jason Salisbury,
who indicated he was having mail delivery issues, didn't get the first one and asked for if
he said he's working on resolving the matter and asked if he could
have until April 1.
Guess the situation is people aren't living there on a regular basis.
I just told him I'd get back to him. I just knew it late afternoon.
So I'm bringing it to the commission.
Do whatever commission
desires.
And the second one was following up on
a cease and desist of 137
shotty millwork gentleman had put up a utility structure and he is in the process of taking it down and I gave him a little extension.
It just is a metal roof and
he wasn't able to really access it in the snow.
So he indicated he would have that down in thirty days and that should be within roughly two weeks from now.
So I have.
>> So on the 44 Whale Road,
when the
property owner says he said it would be resolved by the April 1? Yes, he's
>> told the owners, the
folks that are living in this
RV to be out
by
April 1.
>> Okay.
I guess my thought is that
if they're out by April 1,
if you could give us an update at the March meeting.
Sure.
There's
>> nothing we can do legal
that would be faster than the April 1.
>> Okay. Yeah, I guess I do want to check with the
county attorney's office
and make sure that
we did set into motion something that
I can't stop, that
I have the ability to extend that.
Okay. Yeah. And
>> all I know is I
see the way things sometimes drag on a little bit longer than we expect them to. The April 1 is
incredibly right around the corner at this point. It's late February already.
Leigh Ann, you said you had a comment on one of the training opportunities or something?
>> Oh, yeah. Can you hear me? Yes.
Okay.
Third one says Tuesday two of them have gone by.
The third one says Tuesday, February 24. The twenty fourth,
excuse me, is a Wednesday.
So, Jim, can you find out if it's Tuesday the twenty third or Wednesday the twenty fourth?
Yes.
Okay.
>> That was my only question. Okay. Thank you, Leanne. And any other questions for the zoning agent?
>> Okay. I'm gonna I'm going to go. Thanks. Okay. Yep. Thanks, Leigh Bye.
>> The
Inland Wetlands Water Corners Commission liaison report.
There's a couple of applications
that I would have expected
to see by now.
Hebron Road
being one that's going to come looking for the accessory apartment
and
that was the one I was expecting to see and haven't.
I was a little surprised that all of a sudden the Hendy Road
one
showed up. I did see that,
reading through
minutes from the zoning board of appeals that they
approved
the request
for variance on
building
in the floodplain over there and that was approved.
I know something will be coming our way. I wasn't sure what it was going to be. And so
since
I didn't know and have a chance to review it at all, I didn't want to talk about that tonight.
And that's it. Moving on to miscellaneous.
I'll just share with everybody.
We voted on a budget. I submitted the budget.
And in the budget,
we allotted $5,000
for legal and professional services.
And at the time, we thought we had spent $962
Well, it turns out we've really spent
4,000
in something,
probably about $4,500
So
our
budget submission probably wasn't very good. I'm
trying to figure out exactly
what we've spent the money on but I'm sure that's all spent on
good things.
The earth
will not stop rotating.
I talked to Eric about it and he says,
if need be, we come ask him for more money and we'll get it. I know
money is tight with the town, so we don't want to spend that frivolously.
But one of the things that I was surprised to learn,
two things I was surprised to learn,
That the inland wetlands legal fees and professional services come out of our budget.
I didn't know that.
And when
we have talked about
having
the applicants pay
when we get these professional reviews of applications done and that sort of thing.
And the way that the funding currently works is that fees
associated with applications that come in go into a general fund.
Those
fees wouldn't necessarily go into our
legal professional services fund. So we may be bringing money into the town,
but it doesn't necessarily come into our budget so we can pay the bills for those services.
I think there's a way to change that,
But we're in flux a little bit right this minute with the finance stuff. And so now is not the time to go down that.
But I'm sure Eric would be
willing to help us so that we can make that happen. But his comment was legal advice is normally money well spent.
And
he said,
so don't shortchange
yourself when you need legal advice.
And I think that's good advice. So that would be that. The budget was just a little different than I was expecting it to come out to and wanted to share that with you. So
we're smarter next time around looking at that.
Anybody else have anything else for
a miscellaneous topic here?
Okay, my last comment on that is I appreciate Scott asking us to take a look at the frontage versus width issue. I think that was
a good review of what our regulations really do. There's room for improvement on that and we can go out and make that.
But if
anybody has
thoughts
that
these things are really, you know, these regulations are really goofed up. We ought to take a look at that. Let me know and we can do that.
And with that thought,
I'll call for a motion to adjourn.
All motion to adjourn.
>> Thank you, Scott. Second. Thank you, Susan.
All in favor, aye. Aye. Any
opposed?
Aye. Motion carries,
five-zero-zero.
And thank you everybody for I was hoping we'd be done by nine I'll try to get done there, I certainly don't want to go till ten
We'll call
it a night there. Appreciate the input and
appreciate
the help getting through on the Sheehan property. I do think we did
the right thing there.
And
I'm glad that that one's behind us.
We'll
go forward. Okay. Good night, everybody. Thank you. Good night. Bye.